a particular commentary was brought to
my attention where a writer for the
journal science pointed out the risks of
knack or netal cysteine
supplementation and causing cancer if
you look at the title really makes it
seem like Knack might be falling from
Grace but is it obviously this
commentary especially from a well-known
study publishing Journal isn't written
without evidence so what evidence exists
for this link between Knack consumption
and cancer by the way if you aren't
familiar with Knack it's a molecule by
the full name of N acetylcysteine and
it's gotten quite popular because it has
potent effects increasing our cell's
internal antioxidant defenses
essentially it helps generate a potent
molecule that protects from damage
within our cells called glutathione I'll
leave it at that just know that several
studies have outlined its benefit and
and now here we are with a link to
cancer the commentary points out two
things so one that antioxidants like
Knack aren't always good for you and two
that Knack has been shown to accelerate
cancer growth in multiple models we'll
address both but let's discuss the
second Point first first it's mentioned
that a study this one wherein the
researchers knocked out a gene called
June D in mice
this knockout effectively increases the
amount of damage from oxidative stress
cells experience we even see that
here this is a measure of oxidative
stress with higher numbers being worse
on the horizontal axis we see the
control so normal animals and junee
Knockouts we also see both groups are
given Knack as well as two age groups
young and old as we can see when we
compare the June D knockout m against
the control there's an innately elevated
oxidative stress as predicted by that
particular Gene knockout you'll also
notice that Knack reduces oxidative
stress in all old mice as well as young
mice with this knockout but has no
effect in young control
mice so that all seems like good news so
where's the cancer scare well here it is
here the researchers are measuring the
amount of cell division using a marker
called
ki67 ki67 is a protein only found in
dividing cells the higher the more cell
division generally speaking we have the
same conditions as before and notice how
Knack increases cell division across the
board this is also true for this adk
condition which are mice with lung
adenocarcinoma which is a type of cancer
they already have severalfold
more cell division but they also
experience even more with Knack addition
in addition animals fed Knack had a
slightly increased rate of cancer
generation based on other data
apparently this isn't the first study to
show Knack and other antioxidants
accelerate cancer growth although also
in Mouse models so this is definitely
food for thought but how should we
contextualize this well there's a few
important things to be said and then
we'll discuss the first point about
antioxidants not always being a benefit
to health so first as some will no doubt
already have commented these are Mouse
studies it's tough to immediately
translate that to humans second if we
look at the human studies wherein
participants are given Knack the vast
majority report positive outcomes across
a huge array of outcomes and clinical
conditions third if you look at metrics
related to cancer in humans like DNA
damage and mitochondrial Health they
tend to improve and by pretty
significant amounts finally fourth it's
true that we don't have any long-term
studies investigating cancer risk so is
there still a possibility that These
Warnings could come true definitely
however the randomized control studies
up to now indicate that the evidence is
trending in the opposite direction and
that includes other Mouse studies as
well but what about this mention of
antioxidants not always being good for
us well actually this isn't
news there's uh some truth to that idea
antioxidants like Knack are generally
considered a benefit for their abilities
of reducing oxidizing or damaging
molecules but they can be overabundant
which isn't wanted when some of those
oxidizing molecules also help our cells
function it's a matter of balance so
where do I land everything considered
here well my stance on Knack has not
changed I can see how this commentary
might have a few head scratching but I
appreciate The physionic Insider that
brought this to my attention uh if you
haven't joined the physionic Insiders
consider it by the way because it's this
kind of material that you'll get exposed
to along with my other work podcasts
articles and more at any rate I
appreciate having this brought up
because I even said this when I first
started covering Knack studies more
specifically glac which is a another
iteration of knack but that Knack or
glac only has evidence for its use if
you're over the age of like 50 to 60 and
Beyond or if you're maybe a younger
person dealing with some chronic
condition this probably isn't a
supplement to take if you're already
young and healthy and although I
hesitate to bring up these data again
because they're in mice but notice that
the young mice experienced no
antioxidant benefit of knack and that
held true in short-term human studies as
well so this evidence doesn't really
budge me it actually solidifies my
perspective further until I actually see
human evidence indicating a cancer risk
anyway I thought I'd share and I cover
more on Knack and its health effects in
humans right here I'll catch you over
there
[Music]